Guide to the Anne Nelson-Black papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Anne Nelson-Black papers
1945-2004
MS 1444
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
17.08
(20 containers)
The papers consist of material from El Salvador, including guerrilla propaganda, internal guerrilla memoranda, and U.S. and Salvadoran government documents; material from Puerto Rico relating to the Cerro Maravilla case and the Culebra island controversy; and documents on the 1981-1982 national elections of Honduras, Costa Rica, Guatemala, El Salvador, Mexico, and the Dominican Republic.
Nelson, Anne, 1954-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Anne Nelson-Black, 1986 and 1991. Transferred from the Latin American Collection Curator, 2016.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Anne Nelson was born in Fort Sill, Oklahoma, and grew up in Lincoln, Nebraska. She graduated from Yale University in 1976. As a journalist, Black covered wars in El Salvador and Guatemala, contributing articles and photographs to numerous publications. Nelson is married to author George Black.
Arrangement
Arranged by record type.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of material from El Salvador, including guerrilla propaganda, internal guerrilla memoranda, and U.S. and Salvadoran government documents; material from Puerto Rico relating to the Cerro Maravilla case and the Culebra island controversy; and documents on the 1981-1982 national elections of Honduras, Costa Rica, Guatemala, El Salvador, Mexico, and the Dominican Republic.
Central America; Costa Rica -- Politics and government -- 1948-1986; Cuba; Dominican Republic -- Politics and government; El Salvador -- Politics and government -- 1979-1992; Guatemala -- Politics and government -- 1945-1985; Honduras -- Politics and government -- 1933-1982; Mexico -- Politics and government -- 1970-1982; Puerto Rico -- Foreign relations -- United States; Puerto Rico -- Politics and government -- 1952-1998; United States -- Foreign relations -- Puerto Rico; Authors; Nelson, Anne, 1954-
- Original accession
  - Research files (Box 1–2)
- Additional material, 1978-1986, undated; Accession 1993-M-051; 3.75 linear feet (4 boxes)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Received from Anne Nelson-Black, 1991 Mar 26.
  - Photocopies of official documents pertaining to the Cerro Maravilla case, 1978-1984 (Box 1)
  - Research materials pertaining to the Cerro Maravilla Case, 1978-1985 (Box 1)
  - Research materials pertaining to the Cerro Maravilla Case, 1978-1985 (Box 2)
  - Subject files pertaining to Cuba and Central America, Late 1970s-1986 (Box 3)
  - Untitled manuscript by Jorge Valls on Batista's coup d'état in Cuba, Undated (Box 3)
  - Research materials pertaining to OAS and Puerto Rico, 1978-1980s (Box 4)
  - "Persecution of the Puerto Rican Independence Movement and their Leaders by the Counterintelligence Program (COINTELPRO) of the United States Federal Bureau of Investigation, 1960-1971", Undated (Box 4)
  - Refugees/underground railroad, 1980-1982 (Box 4)
  - Sandinista manuals on education, 1980 (Box 4)
  - State department/banks, 1980-1981 (Box 4)
- Additional Material, 1945-2004; Accession 2016-M-076
  - Correspondence, Interviews, Notes, 1976-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Research Notes, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Murder Under Two Flags: Research Materials, 1979-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Murder Under Two Flags: Reviews, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Film: Show of Force, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Life" Article and Nelson Biographical Material, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript, "Story of Cerro Maravilla", 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Partial Manuscript: Murder Under Two Flags, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Nelson Columbia University Class Assignments, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photos, 1980-1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Journalism: Research Materials, 1979-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photography: Research Materials, 1977-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Clippings Notebook, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Research Materials, 1977-1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Central America Research Materials, 1976-1982 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Central America: Research Materials, 1983-1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Cuba: Research Materials, 1970-1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Cuba: Omega 7, 1976-1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - El Salvador
    - El Salvador: Research Materials I, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - El Salvador: Research Materials II, 1980-1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - El Salvador: Research Materials III, 1980-1985 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - El Salvador: Research Materials IV, 1980-1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - El Salvador: Research Materials V, 1979-1986 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - El Salvador: Research Materials and Nelson's Notes, 1981-1986 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - El Salvador: Death Squads, 1980-1986 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - El Salvador: Rene Tamsen Disappearance, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - El Salvador: Briefing Book, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Guatemala: Research Materials I, 1965-1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Guatemala: Research Materials II, 1982-1986 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Honduras: Research Materials I, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Honduras: Research Materials II, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Nicaragua
    - Nicaragua: Research Materials I, 1979-1985 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Nicaragua: Research Materials II, 1979-1986 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Nicaragua: Research Materials III, 1979-1985 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Latin America: Research Materials I, 1981-1982 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Latin America: Research Materials II, 1975-1986 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Legal Papers: Puerto Rico
    - Legal Depositions I, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Legal Depositions II, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Legal Depositions III, 1998-1999 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Legal Depositions IV, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Legal Depositions V, 1997-1998 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Legal Depositons VI, 1996-1998 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Legal Exhibits, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Puerto Rico
    - Puerto Rico: Reserach Materials, A-B, 1966-1983 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Puerto Rico: Research Materials, C-F, 1967-1985 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Puerto Rico: Research Materials, G-J, 1945-1984 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Puerto Rico: Research Materials, K-M, 1972-1986 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Puerto Rico: Research Materials, N-R, 1970-1984 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Puerto Rico: Research Materials, S, 1965-1975 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Puerto Rico: Research Materials,T-W, 1945-1986 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Cerro Maravilla: Research Materials, 1983-1997 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Puerto Rico: Miscellaneous Research Materials, Annotated, 1995-1997 (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
  - Newspapers
    - El Caribe (Dominican Republic), 1984 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - El Independiente (El Salvador), 1980 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - News Gazette (El Salvador), 1980-1981 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - News Gazette (El Salvador), 1982-1985 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - T-Shirts
    - T-Shirt: Salvador Press Corps, 1980-1989 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - T-Shirt: Reagan Visit to Brazil, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - T-Shirt: Cerro Maravilla, 1978-1984 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Story Corps
    - Lapel Buttons, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - StoryCorps Sampler, 2004; 1 (Box 10, Folder 5A)
  - Pressed Tin Folkart From Penal Mariona, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Broadsides, 1905-1915
    - Carta al Presidente Manuel Estrada Cabrera, 1905 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Club "2 de Abril," de Chiquimula, 1915 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Presidente Manuel Estrada Cabrera, from Club Político "La Gratitud", 1915 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Manifesto de Presidente Manuel Estrada Cabrera, A sus conciudadanos, 1911 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Central American maps, 1974-1978 (Box 13)
  - Posters, 1980-1985 (Folder 14)